Why Do We Live? to Give to Others?
Since I was young,
I thought a lot about why we live.
I came to the conclusion
that we live to give to others.
I think that gives reason to living.
And I think that's necessary
for everyone to be happy.
But when it comes to actually doing that,
I have to consider my family.
My family doesn't feel
the same way as I do.
It's actually not easy
for me to give as much as I can.
And I don't think my wife and children
are quite ready to do so.
How much should I start giving back
in this situation?
Your question doesn't quite make sense.
Why do we live?
"We live to give."
That's not the answer.
Why do we live?
We just do. That's the answer.
Do you understand?
We don't live because there's a reason.
Will you die tonight
if you have no reason to live?
There is no reason for living.
You're thinking wrong.
You think you have to have a reason
to keep living. That's not so.
Before you think about any reason..
Were you born for a reason?
Or were you just born?
You were just born.
People are just born first.
Then they later try to find
the reason for being born.
Existence comes first. Always.
Do you understand?
So the question of why we live is
not the right question in the first place.
Why do we live?
We just do.
If you must ask, we just live.
If you still ask, we live
because we're not dead.
(Audience laughs)
Why?
Living comes first.
Secondly, since we're living
because we're not dead,
how should we live?
How?
Should we live in greed?
Or should we give back to others?
Should we live happily? Suffer?
Or help others?
This concerns HOW we should live.
Not WHY we live.
How should we live?
If you like being greedy,
you can live that way.
If you like giving back to others,
But the point is this:
That choice is secondary.
Giving back or not giving back
is secondary.
Living in happiness or in suffering
is the key point.
(Sunim) Are you sometimes unhappy?
(Audience) We are.
(Sunim) Do you like that or not?
(Audience) We don't like it.
(Sunim) Do you like being happy?
(Audience) We like it.
You like it, right?
Everyone wants to be happy.
Then what makes you happy?
That's how we can look at it.
Maybe giving back makes you happy.
Maybe just being the receiver
makes you less happy.
Then you can give back as you like.
If receiving help from others
makes you happy,
then you can just do that.
There is no set rule to which is right.
(Questioner) Are you saying
it's different for each person?
You can do as you like.
Whatever you like.
So if you want to give back, you can.
But if your wife is against it,
Then giving back makes you happy,
but it makes her unhappy
and leads to fighting, right?
Then you have to weigh the two options.
If the pleasure of giving back outweighs
the pain of fighting with your wife,
Then you can give back and not worry
about how your wife feels.
But if the pain of fighting with your wife
outweighs the pleasure of giving back,
You shouldn't give back
even if you want to.
You have to make a compromise
to live with your wife.
That's life.
There are no set rules.
You shouldn't live only by the rules of ethics
or morals for the sake of living by the rules.
If you have a wife,
you need to find what works for both of you.
There is no right or wrong.
If you're not willing to make compromises,
then you should live alone.
To live together, you have to compromise.
Life changes
from living alone to living with someone.
You can't be the same person.
For example, if you're a single man,
you can have coffee with one woman one day
and another woman the next.
But once you marry, can you do that?
No, you can't.
"Why not? I'm a person."
You can't say that.
(Audience laughs)
Such a man shouldn't have the privilege of
marrying or living with another person.
All of you may get married, right?
But once you become a monk,
can you marry?
You can't.
"Why not? I'm a person."
You can't say that.
(Sunim) If you want to marry,
don't be a monk and you can get married.
(Sunim) It's not that you can't marry.
I'm saying you have to choose one or the other.
You live to live accordingly.
If you married,
you have to compromise with your wife,
no matter what you want to do.
(Questioner) I'm sorry to take
too much time, but I have another question.
(Questioner) My aunt is unconscious
and hospitalized right now.
(Questioner) She has almost
no chance of recovery.
She's been on a respirator
for 3 months now.
If she's suffering so much for so long,
is it better to take her off the respirator?
No.
Even if the family comes to an agreement
to take her off the respirator,
if the doctor says he can't do that
because of hospital policy, you can't.
If the family agrees,
you may ask the doctor to take her off.
But if your family can't come
to an agreement, the doctor can't do that.
It's not something
you can decide on your own.
If you want her off,
you have to discuss it with your family.
If your family agrees,
then you have to consult the doctor.
But if the hospital policy doesn't allow it,
you can't do it.
Do you understand?
So, apart from the question of why or how,
You discuss it with the family and
decide based on how they feel,
rather than how the patient feels.
Why?
Because the patient is not conscious.
You can discuss with family and
make a decision with the doctor.
(Questioner) Okay. Thank you.
(Audience Applause)