I'm told my child is ill due to a bad name.
What should I do?
(Questioner) Hello, I'm the only man
who ask about their own child
I'm a father of two children.
My second child has been severely ill.
He was hospitalized the day he was born,
and has continued treatment after being discharged.
I have a family member that goes to a temple a lot.
The temple monk heard of my son
and said that my child has a bad name.
He said that the name will continue
his illness for the rest of his life.
The monk hence created
a new name for him.
I've always been capable of
making decisions throughout life.
But since this matter involves
my child's issues, I'm lost as to what to do.
His current name was properly
created by a traditional name maker.
And yet the monk claims
the name is very bad.
He came up with a new name and
recommends we change our child's name.
Since you are here, I'd like to
seek your thoughts on this.
Just change it. What's there to ask?
If he says it will be good then change it.
But you shouldn't think a name
change will cure your child's illness.
If you do, you'll resent the monk for it. You'll
feel like the name change has done no good.
Do you really think changing a name
would influence your child's health?
Use your common sense.
But if you feel like changing names
would be something you'd do
out of slight hope under difficult
circumstances, try it out.
Many of us have two names
while we grow up, do we not?
People used to name their
daughters using certain letters
hoping it would make them their
last daughter (and have a son)
Try using a new name in the same manner.
When you become a Buddhist,
you get a new Buddhist name, do you not?
You can try a new name the same way.
(Sunim) Regardless of whether
the name will help you or not,
(Sunim) you value the monk's opinion.
And the monk said so,
so you might as well follow.
You ask me my thoughts even after
the monk gave you a name.
You'll probably ask some other monk
his opinion of my opinion.
One gives you a name,
another may say the name's not good.
Then you'd ask another how he thinks.
Are you trying to start a fight
among us all? What for?
Why the hassle? If he says
it's a good name, just call him that.
Why ask around? What for?
My wife and I've been hesitant to change
the name for the last two months.
What does your wife think?
(Questioner) She leaves it all up to me.
Which way do you think
she's leaning towards?
(Questioner) I'm not exactly sure.
She says the current name is fine.
Then she says the new name seems ok too.
If changing a name changes your fortune,
everyone would change their name.
Why work hard?
Why would a monk shave
his head and practice?
All they need to do is change their name
and they'd reach enlightenment.
Try the new name without
expecting too much of it.
I understand where you're coming
from as a parent of an ill child.
But such weak thoughts
raise these problems.
My thoughts are simple.
If he says the name's good,
try using it in your daily life.
You already have a name
registered, do you not?
leave the registered name as is
and try using the new name.
If good things happen, then you
can officially change it later on.
Why change it now? Just try calling it.
I will try that. Thank you.
Think of parenting this way.
Let's say your child is tall,
handsome and does well in school.
If he's tall, handsome and smart,
would the parents only like him?
Or would all the neighbors like him?
All the neighbors would like him.
Hence it wouldn't be a
parent's mindset to like him
A parent should love a child even if he's
short, ugly, stupid and has a bad temper.
Even if the whole world hates him,
a parent should love him.
That is what a parent is.
If not, you're nothing more than
a neighbor. You're not a parent.
In the same manner, it would be
nice to have a healthy child.
And yet the child was born
with a disability or a serious illness.
Obsessing over making the child
healthy only makes the child suffer.
The whole family also suffers
because of the child. Do you understand?
So when you have a child with disability,
think to yourself, 'He could have been
abandoned if he were born elsewhere'
'But I'm a Buddhist/Christian, hence will
think of it as my calling and care for him
A parent takes care of a child whether
he/she is with a disability,
a girl or a boy, smart or not.
A parent doesn't discriminate.
That is a mind of a parent.
That is also the mind of a Buddha.
If you are too held up on the issue,
it only brings anxieties to your household.
Happily accept the disability
and shortcoming as is,
and care for the child in the condition
he is in until his time is done.
If you approach it with such an attitude,
you won't be as frustrated.
As you try clutching at a straw
then you are experiencing
such difficulties.
Do you understand?
Listening to you speak, you're
not in the mindset of a parent.
You are in the mindset of a neighbor.
A parent shouldn't love
their child for getting better,
and love less for not getting better.
A parent should always
encourage their child.
When he asks of things,
you should say
"What do I know?
You know better than me, son."