Qualifications for a Good Spouse
My question is what are the
qualifications to be a good spouse?
I guess I'm past my prime age
for getting married.
Regarding marriage, I've had
this vague idea since I was young that
as long as my partner and I have
the same values and pursuits,
it can be happy marriage.
But, as I reached a marrying age,
I found myself seeking advice
from people around me.
The bottom line was
about the material things.
They said,
"A man should have at least this much."
They say,
"Unless you are financially well
prepared, you cannot be happy."
Although I have my own values,
it's hard to deny such things
as I get older.
I ask for your advice on how
I should respond to such advice.
The qualifications of marriage...
First, one has to be
over 17-18 years of age.
(Questioner) Yes.
That's legally.
Biologically, one has to be
over 15 or 16.
Legally and ethically speaking,
one needs to be over 20.
Do you understand?
This is the qualification of marriage.
(Audience Laughter)
Next, the qualification of the mind
is the most important.
You have to know
how to adjust to the other person.
You have to be willing to
make adjustments.
If you want to go,
but your partner doesn't,
you should be prepared not to go.
If you want to go to the beach, but your
partner wants to go to the mountain,
you should be willing
to go to the mountain.
This is the most critical
qualification of marriage...
being able to adjust.
So, unless you are ready
to adjust to the other person,
you should not get married.
You don't need adjustment
to have sex only.
Animals don't adjust for each other
because they only copulate
to preserve their own species.
They don't need such things
like a marriage relationship.
So, animals don't need to
prepare to make adjustments.
But, marriage is a community.
Two people living together,
whether they are two men,
two women, or a man and a woman,
is different from animals living together.
Even two men living together
as roommates
is a community, like a marriage.
If a man and a woman live together
just to copulate,
it's at the level of animal nature.
But, the essence of marriage
doesn't lie in copulation,
but in forming a community.
People form cooperative relationships
because living together is
better than living alone.
And the reproduction
for the preservation of species
is added to marriage.
That's why one has to be over 15
or 20 from the biological point of view.
From a community point of view,
one has to learn to adjust.
Are you ready to adjust
to the other person?
Are you willing to go
to the beach for your spouse
even you want to go to the mountain?
(Questioner) Yes.
(Audience Laughter)
People are laughing
at your quick answer.
Why?
Because it's hard to do in real life.
(Audience Laughter)
Trouble starts with a very small thing.
Trouble starts if the wife likes to hang
her clothes in the closet
the moment she takes it off,
but the husband leaves it
wherever he takes it off.
The husband says
his wife's cooking lacks salt
while she thinks it's just right.
And she accuses him
for having a salty diet.
Conflicts arise from
these kinds of things.
One person says the room is too
hot while the other says it's too cold.
"Turn on the AC." "No, turn it off."
Same thing with cleaning the house.
One insists the other
to take a shower before bedtime,
while the other says taking a shower
once every three days is enough.
Marriage is difficult due to this
kind of conflicts, not the other stuff.
You don't need to own a condo or a car.
They are secondary.
Marriages fail these days
no matter how well they prepare for it
because people place those
secondary things at the center,
those are irrelevant to marriage.
In some cases, they break up
during wedding preparations.
In other cases, the couples get divorced
upon returning from their honeymoon.
What you call
the qualifications of marriage
are actually irrelevant to married life.
Animals live and raise their young
even in such a small nest under a tree.
How did our ancestors live?
Did they have everything ready
before getting married?
No. You don't need to have
any material things ready.
Let's say you each
live in studio apartments.
By living together,
you already save one rent, right?
How about dining tables?
You don't need two, so you save on one.
So you benefit.
Also, instead of each
cleaning a room daily,
you take turns,
so one rest for a day.
Sharing all the duties like this
brings benefits to life.
A baby grows with a mother's love,
not a fancy cradle.
A baby doesn't need
Japanese baby formula
or Japanese diapers.
Babies don't know such things.
Marriages fail
because we are concerned about
what is irrelevant to marriage.
So, are you willing to adjust for
the person you are going to marry?
A pretty person is nice
when you are just dating, but,
the one you will live together must
have practical abilities for daily living.
A woman knows how to cook,
and a man helps with house cleaning.
These things are important in
marriage because it is communal living.
There's a saying that even a pretty
flower looks good only for a day or two.
A rag is for cleaning,
so it should absorb water to clean dirt.
What would happen
if you made a nice rag out of gold?
Would it clean well or not?
It would not.
You will have to leave
the gold rag at home
and go borrow one that absorbs water.
That's why some men have affairs
after marrying a pretty woman.
The same applies to women.
What happens to a woman
who marries into a rich family?
You might think a woman does well,
if she marries up in social status to
a son of a governor, high-ranking
academic, high government official,
a politician or a rich man.
But, the woman would be
treated almost like a maid instead of
being accepted as a member
of the family or a daughter-in-law.
Her life would be
a servant obeying a master.
So, her spirit withers.
She has to follow her
in-laws decisions on everything.
On the other hand, a woman
who marries into a poor family with
not much education,
would be treated with respect.
I'm not saying that's 100% the case.
But, generally that's how it is.
In other words, you have to consider
how much freedom you would have.
Do you want to be a servant
who gets to spend money?
Or, do you want to be your own master
living a simple life in a small house?
Most women say they want
to be their own masters,
but choose to be servants.
Most of those women score low
on marriage satisfaction surveys.
Almost all of them
suffer from depression.
So, first, are you ready to
adjust to the other person?
Second, until now, you were
your mother's son, your father's son.
But, once you get married,
you become a husband to a woman.
Being a mother's son and
a woman's husband at the same time,
is like having a mistress on the side.
You have to abandon one woman.
A married woman
is a stranger to her family.
This old idea is good,
even it is not held any longer.
The problem is for men
not being able to sever his family ties.
Men don’t sever their ties,
so I tell them to cut them off.
Young women these days rely on
their parents support after her marriage.
The more a man marries up,
the more he suffers,
due to his in-laws' involvement.
Adjusting to one’s spouse
is hard enough.
It makes the married life very difficult,
if you have to adjust to in-laws also.
It's like South and North Korea.
It's hard enough to adjust to each other,
but, we have to adjust to the U.S.
behind South Korea
and China behind North Korea.
What does this mean? It means
we have not yet gained independence.
We are like a subordinate state
subject to powerful nations.
Most of today's sons and daughters
are like the subordinate states.
They are prone to divisions and conflicts
under the influence of strong powers.
When you are unsure,
it's better to live alone like me.
You shouldn't marry
just because others do.
Second, you should take a clear stance
as the man responsible for the family.
The same applies to women.
You can't maintain your new family
if you habitually depend on your parents
economically or psychologically
as you did as a child.
It's like a company makes its own
decisions after gaining independence.
Don't get married
if you don't have this mindset.
This is the important part of
marriage preparation.
The family background, the type of car,
and the type of job are all secondary.
Make adjustments for each other
and take small steps together.
(Questioner) Thank you.
Those of you suffering
from your marriage
wish you had heard this
before getting married, right?
Do you know what we call it?
To put it nicely,
"You are like a rat who ate rat poison."
Don't blame anybody else.
You are all hurting yourselves.