I avoid people I don't like.
How can I change myself?
(Questioner) Hello,
I'm a freshman in college.
When building relationships
in high school,
I used to hang out with friends I like.
I wouldn't bother mingling with people
that I couldn't click with.
I continued to do the same in college.
I'd hang out with only those I can connect
with, and not with those that I couldn't.
As I started meeting more people
in college,
I found more people
I couldn't get along with.
The more find them, the more I feel like
it has to do with my personality.
The more I think
I have an abnormal personality,
the more I feel afraid to meet people.
Should I change myself?
Your personality is not abnormal.
Your personality is what it is,
but that doesn't make you abnormal.
You are who you are.
When you were in high school,
your relationships formed by
being placed in the same class for a year.
Hence it was fine to hang out with
only those whom you could connect with.
Now that you're in college, you meet more
people and develop broader relationships.
In elementary school,
you would've had 3 kids in your class
that you couldn't get along with.
Back then it was 3 out of 30 kids.
Now that you know 300 people,
you have 30 people
you don't get along with.
So there is no real problem.
It's just that you know more people now,
hence you have more people
you don't get along with.
Every living person in this world
has a different personality.
If you only want to form relationships
with those you like,
you can do so by limiting yourself
to a narrow scope.
You can accept the limits
without wanting more in your life.
Do you understand?
Assume you dislike a certain professor.
You don't need to get along with him,
but instead you'll have to accept the fact
that you might not get the best grades.
Assume you dislike your boss at work.
You need to accept the fact that
your relationship with him
may affect your promotion.
The world does not only consist of people
that you get along with.
Such an attitude
does not affect you too much
when you are young
and protected by parents.
Once you're over 20 and independent,
your attitude may affect you negatively.
Knowing this,
should you change your ways or not?
It's not that you should change
as you are wrong.
It's just that
it's inconvenient for you not to.
In marriage, we change ourselves
to adjust to a life as a pair.
We change ourselves
not because we are wrong.
Is it easy to change yourself?
(Questioner) It is not.
(Sumin) Yes, it is not
Personalities are a form of a habit.
Habits are developed
over a long period of time.
For example, the inability to
express emotions is a habit.
It is karma.
Such habits are very hard to change.
They don't change even with
strong willpower.
They don't change by attempting
once or twice.
Hence there is the saying
"Resolutions last three days".
How to change? First, Just as habits are
formed over a long period of time,
changing habits also take
a long period of time and practice.
Try talking to people
you don't get along with.
You will feel resistance
within yourself, will you not?
Even so, continue trying.
If you don't like snakes,
spend an hour every morning
playing with snakes.
(Audience Laughter)
Touch them, kiss them and
carry them around your neck.
You'll be repulsed at first but
will that doable as you continue or not?
(Sunim) It's doable.
If it works with snakes,
why won't it work with people?
It will work just fine.
All you need is practice.
Try practicing over a long period of time.
Once you do, your former
habits will change to new ones
Second, you should also try
stimulating your unconscious mind.
Habits are formed
in the unconscious mind.
They are not thoughts of the brain,
they are reactions from the heart.
Assume you've deeply acknowledged
a certain wrongdoing.
You say "Ah, this was the problem!".
Assume you've acknowledged it from
the heart and not from the mind.
Tears start flowing.
You're able to change yourself through
practice in 100 days instead of 3 years.
My dharma talks can be delivered
in theory by a college professor.
But my talks touch you on an emotional level
rather than as logic, do they not?
This is why you're able to find small changes
in your lives by listening to my talks.
Small habits can change
by being emotionally touched.
And yet habits formed in early childhood
do not change regardless of
such emotional stimulation.
They are lodged in the
deep unconscious mind.
It is unlikely that
you can change such early habits.
Hence we say
'God given personalities cannot be change'.
Then is it impossible to change?
No, it can be done.
Then how can it be changed?
Our survival instinct roots much deeper
than our unconscious mind.
When we feel that
our survival is threatened,
we become capable of changing habits.
The fact that Jesus fasted for 40 days
indicates there had been a threat
to his survival instinct.
The fact that Buddha practiced
severe suffering for 6 years
indicates it threatens
to his survival instinct.
In such way people were able to
change their karmic habits
which most find impossible to change.
You can also exert a threat
to your survival instinct
if you haven't been interacting with
those that you dislike.
How? You can give yourself
an electric shock.
(Audience Laughter)
If you have a hard time getting up in the
morning even with an alarm clock,
ask your mom to give you an electric shock
a few times every morning.
Will you then be able to hear
the alarm at 5 am or not?
Be honest,
will be hear the alarm or not?
No matter how sound asleep you are,
you will hear the alarm.
The moment you hear it,
your body will immediately react to it.
You'll wake up instantly.
So no need to put effort into it.
Threatening your survival will do.
Young men join the army and change
their worst habits, do they not?
They do. In the army,
you are required to follow strict rules
and regulations without an excuse.
You join the army with a conviction
and understand that
excuses aren't tolerated.
Try saying 'I'm kind of sick'.
It can't be used as an excuse.
Hence during military service,
you're able to overcome your habits.
Now I don't think you will go through
with the electric shock method.
So once you decide to change yourself,
deliberately choose to meet only those
you don't like.
In class, converse with the person
you most dislike.
Say "How have you been?"
If they say they hate you,
say "I like your facial
expression of hatred."
Have lunch with the person you dislike.
Think of it as playing with a snake.
This should be better off than that.
Do you understand?
As you practice persistently,
you'll be able to change yourself.
Will you change yourself
in order to live a broader life?
Are you willing to do undesirable things
knowing they are ultimately
in your interest?
Or would you rather just live according to
your karmic habits regardless of interest?
Would you rather live a life dealing with
only those you like?
The latter option works too.
But you'll have to give up on
certain interests. Understand?
(Questioner) Yes.
(Applause)