I am sensitive to my child's school grades
(Questioner) I enjoyed your appearance
on the TV show 'Healing Camp'.
(Questioner) I also read your book
'A Monk's Wedding Speech'.
(Questioner) It made me think about many
things and brings me here today.
I have a daughter who just
entered elementary school.
I know study itself and good grade
doesn't mean that she'll have a good life.
However, I still get nervous
and stressed out.
At first, I thought it would be fine
for her to rank in the middle.
Still, I had convinced myself that
even if she ranks last in class,
it would be okay.
Despite of this thought,
I am getting irritated at her
mistake in her exam, even one
I get overly sensitive
and scold her with anger.
Sometimes I wonder,
Do I want her to study for herself
or for the sake of my own pride
Even knowing this, I can't
easily let go. What should I do?
(Sunim) You just raised a question.
Do you want her to study
for her own sake?
Or should she study for
your own pride?
(Sunim) Are you confused?
(Questioner) Yes, I'm not sure.
(Sunim) Think more about it.
(Questioner) Maybe I think,
(Questioner) I try not to see
other moms too often.
(Questioner) Because, they say
someone's child received an award,
(Questioner) or someone's child
got praised by the teacher.
(Questioner) However, what I have
heard the most was that..
(Questioner) my daughter had fought
with a friend and got punished.
(Questioner) I'd be OK not to
hear and know that,
(Questioner) or hear it from
my daughter directly,
(Questioner) But hearing such
things from others made me upset.
(Sunim) If she had hit
someone or had fought,
(Sunim) those behaviors
should be corrected.
(Sunim) But think of it this way.
(Sunim) Let say, we select
30 top-performing students,
(Sunim) and put them in one class.
(Sunim) Do they have
the last-placed student or not?
(Questioner) Yes, they have one
(Sunim) If we made a classroom
of 30 worst performing students.
(Sunim) Is there a
first-placed one or not?
(Questioner) Yes
(Sunim) Rankings are not that important.
(Sunim) If you want your child to rank
higher, you should move to the suburbs.
When you move to the suburbs,
she'll immediately rank higher.
Rankings are not meaningful at all.
And children make mistakes.
If you give her pressure,
she makes a mistake even
though she knows the answer.
When you are nervous,
you can't speak very well.
When you tremble, it is hard to
speak out in front of people.
We all know how is like taking exam.
When you're nervous,
you got wrong answer by mistake
The question asks you
to pick the wrong answer,
but you pick the very first right
answer and you move on.
You thought you were supposed
to pick the right one.
Later, you find out you read
the question in apposite way,
So, choose right one instead of
wrong one by mistake
The more nervous you are,
the more likely this happens.
If your child comes home
upset over her grades,
a mother should pat her
daughter's back and say,
"It's fine. It's ok, getting one more
right answer doesn't affect your life"
"If you didn't do well this time,
you can do better next time."
A mother should encourage her child,
instead of jumping up and down,
even more so than your own child.
You're not sensitive
for the sake of your child.
but for your own pride and satisfaction.
Likewise, there is a same feeling
when you speak to other parents.
Your pride gets hurt,
not for your child.
You want them to say your
child is smart and a good kid.
but your expectations aren't met.
A mother should always protect her child
no matter how she gets criticized.
A child is not a puppy nor a possession.
Let say, someone give you
compliments to your clothes.
Are they praising you
or your clothes?
It is the same logic.
The things is you want to hear that
you're a good person.
It's not important to hear that
your clothes are nice,
or that your hair looks gorgeous.
Please stop worthless thinking,
Mother always should be a protector
and the God to her children.
Children should know
their mother will protect them,
when the world may harm them
They should know that
the world may criticize them,
but their mother will still love them.
Only when they feel this way,
they won't long for love.
Most of you don't nurture
your children this way.
Hence, children always feel the lack
of love. You may have felt this way too.
As people seek love, they fall in love to
anyone who give you good cares.
That's why they easily got fraud.
Women who long for love easily
fall in love with players and frauds.
Someone shows a little attention,
they trust and give herself to them.
They lack of objectivity
and seeing people.
Hence, they lead their own
children into unhappiness.
Keep your child preciously.
I'm not saying you should think it's fine
for her to be the lowest in the class.
Regardless of the lowest or the highest,
you should encourage her and let her
know you love her as her mother.
If she fails this time,
you should encourage her
to challenge herself next time.
If she fails again, you should
encourage her once again.
Children may give up and despair,
but they can comeback for
encouragement of their mother.
Don't be stick to class ranking.
Teachers may worry about rankings,
but mothers should not.
You should change your way of thinking.
How are you with your husband?
Are you good to him?
While they are cling to such
unnecessary anxiety on her child,
It is hard to see good wives
for the husbands.
(Sunim) I can tell.
Wives in an amazing relationship with
their husbands focus less on their kids.
When the relationship is not satisfied,
they focus on their children.
So, let your child go and focus
more on your husband. Okay?
You should be good to your
husband from now on,
doing 108 prostrations every morning.
Even if you change your mind,
you'll likely feel sensitive again
when you see you child.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes
You have to do
108 prostrations continuously
Saying "Buddha, my child grow up well.
I have no worries."
Mothers should be positive
towards their children.
If a mother always nags and
treats her child as problematic,
how can a child develop
self-esteem?
They become insecure and consider
themselves unworthy and not good enough.
A child's self-respect breaks down if
a mother criticizes her child constantly
When child grows, they resist.
Please stop bothering your child.
If you have nothing to do, go out
and do your own thing. Play with a dog.
Don't bother your child,
Just encourage her.
I will. Thank you.
If you have seven or eight kids,
do you think you have time to
be worry on those issues? No
Since you have an only child,
you are fussing over her.
If you have a work or
if you are satisfied your relationship,
you would spend more time with
your husband than your child.
But You're not satisfied with your
husband, you have an only child,
So, you are obsessed with your child.
You dress a child in this one and that one
you feed her this one and that one.
You follow her school and
ask to do this and do that.
How should this little child endure this?