Not Easy to Concede
Sunim,
Thank you for your wonderful teaching.
You have told us whoever wants to gain
more should compromise or concede.
But when I am faced with such situation,
it's hard to dismiss the angry feeling and
the feeling that I should react somehow.
By way of example,
my brother had much conflict
with our mother after getting married,
and due to a conflict between his wife
and our mother,
my brother took a portion of
our mother's asset.
I accepted his action thinking,
"He must have had a reason to do it;
he can spend it,"
But I am having difficulties
with thinking that
my brother could get greedy
and he and I could get into dispute.
Our poor relations with North Korea
and its nuclear weapon problem.
Must we give into the demands of others,
knowing that they are not behaving
correctly or fairly?
Or wouldn't it be better
to confront directly
and engage in the fight and confrontation?
Wouldn’t this be better?
Unless, one is a dedicated Buddhist monk,
isn't there a limitation to our ability
to always compromise and/or concede?
(Audience Laughter)
The mind of this questioner is
everyone's common mind.
However, giving away everything
when asked is Buddha's mind.
Giving everything that is asked of.
However, it is our reality
that we cannot live like Buddha.
So we can choose from here on
to manifest Buddha's mind
and act with such whenever possible.
Even if we are not yet at that level,
we ought to try and raise our level a bit
by adopting Buddha's mind.
But let us examine our own minds.
When you see your brother
taking the inheritance,
you just remain in an upset state
without the ability
to either fight or bring it back.
You lose the inheritance
and you are also suffering.
But, if you at least,
want to have a peace of mind,
you can tell him "OK, you take it,"
then at least you won't feel bad
even if you lose the money.
Then you won't lose both,
rather just the money.
Wouldn't that be wiser?'
is the question I raise.
If you are determined to get your share of
the assets, then you should fight.
Then you may get the assets
but it would be complicated to fight,
wouldn't it?
You cannot complain
that you are suffering then.
If you do not want to suffer,
you can simply let go of the money.
So, if you want the assets, then fight.
But when you fight with anger,
you are the one who will suffer.
But if you accept that your brother, too,
want this money as you do,
then you will not be as angry.
Not being angry here means,
you will not be suffering.
In that state of mind,
if you choose to obtain your share
of the inheritance guaranteed by law,
instead of fighting,
you can talk it out or go to court.
You get stressed with damaged relationship
with your brother,
but you will gain some money.
Then, you have to choose:
to gain money or
good relationship with your brother.
You just have to choose
to gain one and lose the other.
In general, most of us lose both of them.
A wise person would take one
and lose the other.
Bodhisattvas would actually gain both
by letting go of both.
So, people say,
"Doesn't that mean we lose everything
if we follow Buddha's teaching?"
There is no gain or loss
in Buddha's teaching.
Drop the idea of gain.
It belongs to your parents anyway,
it wasn't yours.
So your brother's desire
to have the assets
and your desires
to have them too are the same.
You must recognize
that both of you are same.
You think it is unfair for him to take
but is fair for you to take.
You suffer
because you think your brother is greedy.
As a younger brother,
you think things should be divided evenly,
while your brother thinks
that he deserves more.
Because he wants more, the younger brother
thinks his brother is being greedy.
The older brother thinks
in the old fashioned way.
The older brother should deserve more.
You ask the younger brother
is thinking in a modern way.
You follow the recently changed law.
Your brother follows the old law.
Women, these days, want to divide
things evenly following the new law.
While the men want
to retain the old fashioned way.
(Audience Laughter)
That is why if you ask each person,
they have reasons to justify their points.
Even the things that seem unjust to me,
another person can find the justification
and will be able to rationalize it.
That's why people act this way.
From my point of view, I get upset.
But from other's point of view,
we can come to understand.
When we say, " I understand,"
there are two ways to interpret this:
I understand but do not agree.
I understand and agree as well.
There are reasons for
the North Korean government
to develop and launch nuclear missiles.
It is understandable.
It is understandable, but is it desirable?
You would think it is not desirable.
You often suffer
because you refuse to understand.
But I can understand as a monk.
Some other people even agree with it
I, myself, do not agree with it.
I am critical of the situation.
Possession of a nuclear weapon
is a loss for you and us.
It is a foolish move.
But I can understand
the people behaving in foolish ways.
The arguments between a couple,
for example
I understand
But is that a good way to behave?
I certainly do not think so.
But since I can understand,
I continue to accept requests
for advice on such matters.
I think, "that would be possible."
But because I think it is not desirable,
I often suggest
"Don't do it that way
and try doing it this way"
I wouldn't be able to counsel
if I didn't understand.
That's is where the difference lies.
Understanding does not mean
that you condone what the other is doing.
You come to understand
the other person's point of view.
You can understand the other's situation
from his point of view.
If you understand,
then you can begin to communicate.
If you don't understand,
then you don't feel like talking.
That is why, first, try to understand.
At the very least, try to understand…
Who will benefit from this understanding?
You will.
You will not experience the tightening
of your heart and you will not be angry.
So, choose one between these two attitudes
At least, have one thing under control
and decide
to fight over the money or not.
If you want both,
then fight and see what happens.
If you are ok with only one of these
two positions, you can give up the other.
Doesn't this seem to be a wise choice?
Does it seem foolish?
(Audience Laughter)
It would be good to behave wisely,
especially for the sly ones…
Would it be easier to assert the fairness
about the inheritance with wise manner?
Or would it be easier to assert one's
position with an angry and enraged state?
It would be easier
to choose the first one, right?
It would be easier to convince
your brother through communication
but also convince the judge.
“I understand why you come to act
this way, dear brother."
“But I, too want to receive at least the
amount that is legally due to me, etc."
If you speak in this manner, the judge
will think your points are justified.
By way of an example.
That is why it is better to act wisely.