The Meaning of Not Interfering
Among your talks, you mention that
we ought not to interfere
in other people's lives.
Thinking that "other people"
as anyone other than myself,
I tend to neglect my relationships
with other people.
In that case, when and
how do we use the word, family?
Wouldn't I become too indifferent
and give up on others
with this way of thinking?
I would like to hear your thoughts
about this matter.
When we say that
we love our children,
there are two kinds of
meaning in that love.
One can mean a real sacrifice
in order to help our children.
The child is in the center, you
are secondary in importance.
You call it love when you say that you
would do anything to help your child.
But there in that statement,
you are actually in the center
and your child is secondary.
You demand that
the child follow your need.
This is selfishness.
This is your desire.
This is not love.
In Buddhism, we call this
obsessive attachment.
So, the parents can cause
harm to their children
through this obsessive attachment.
Instead of helping the children,
parents harm the children.
So, I say, "Let go of your
obsessive attachment."
When I say this, you say,
"How can I let go of the attachment?
He is my child!"
Then, I say what?
"Do not interfere
in another person's life!"
This means, even though it's your child,
you ought to respect
the individual person in him.
So, not interfering
in other people's lives means,
even though you are the parent,
respect your child
as an independent person.
Though he is your child,
respect his own independent personhood.
Though he is your husband,
respect him as an independent person.
Respect the individual's personhood.
In the name of my child,
my parents, my husband, my wife
we often do not respect
the other's individual personhood.
So, I say: do not interfere
in other people's lives.
Turn it upside down:
respect the other's individuality.
Respect individuality.
For example, you give birth to a child.
The child goes to kindergarten to
elementary school and middle school.
You have to take care
of this child or not?
"Well, go ahead and live your life"
Would you say that
and leave the child alone?
"The Sunim said that it's your life,"
"I'm not going to interfere in your life,
enjoy your life"
Would you say like this?
That is not what I mean.
A young child needs to be
taken care of by someone.
So, a mother needs to
take care of her child.
Even a motherless child needs
to be cared for. Right?
It is necessary that someone
should care for the child.
We name those who take care of the child
as mothers or parents.
So, you don't care for someone
only because you gave birth to him
When you encounter a child who
needs care, you take care of the child.
It doesn't matter
whether the child is yours or not.
Because it is the law of nature.
But the child you are caring for
is growing to be an adolescent.
What is the meaning of adolescence?
Male physical characteristics appear
in boys and female ones for girls.
Boys can have erections,
and girls start developing breasts.
Their bodies grow into those of adults.
As the bodies grow,
their mental states, too, evolve
so that they become more self-centered
and do things on their own.
The child who always listened
to his mom before,
starts saying "No"
He will do things in spite
of being told not to
or not do the things
he is told to do.
So, the child begins to have
conflict with his mother.
Does this mean that the child
has become a bad child?
It is not that he has grown into
a bad child in the middle school.
This is a natural phenomenon.
So, what to do about this?
The child has done
whatever he was told before,
but now in order to make
his own decisions,
he needs to have his
own experiences.
He needs to experience making
mistakes and getting hurt.
He may get hurt physically, too.
It is a period when he learns to make
his own decisions by his own experiences.
During this time,
a parent must hold your tongue
even if you think he'd make a mistake.
Even if he gets hurt, loses money,
or gets hurt physically,
watching the child go through those
processes with cool detachment
is the genuine love for the child.
But a mother,
focusing only on her feelings of
not wanting to see
her child get hurt,
and out of the habit of caring for
a small child,
keeps telling him what to do.
It's hard on the parents
caring for the child,
and the child loses the chance
to experience things on his own.
In the end, it will be
a great loss for the child.
You have created someone
who is unable to live his own life.
The parent will not know what to do.
The kid will do what he will.
According to whatever he thinks.
Then, you need to step back
with cool detachment.
You help when the child asks for help.
If his leg is broken and he asks to
be taken to the hospital, you help.
Otherwise, leave him alone
when he gets something like scratches.
So, when he comes asking for help,
then you help.
Even when he asks for help,
you need to think things through.
You must be detached,
so that the child can become independent.
Moreover, when he becomes an adult,
you need to cut the emotional ties.
If you interfere in his life
just because he is your child
and bestowing a heavy
burden on him,
he will not be able to
grow up properly.
And it will be hard for you
as well to interfere.
He will resist and push back.
Then the conflict will be hard to handle.
When I listen carefully, though you think
the problem is with the child,
I see the problem is yours.
So, I say, "Don't interfere
in other people's lives."
"You just live your life well."
"Why are you interfering in other's life
when you don't live well yourself?"
So, when I say this,
you may think that
it is not in accordance
with Buddha's teaching
which says to think of
all being as yourself
or look upon them with
great compassion, etc.
I think your question comes
from these thoughts.
It seems like you might
misunderstood what I have said.
In addition, when you are married,
Do you think the husband must do
100% of what the wife asks of him?
Doesn't he have his own life even
though he cooperates with the wife?
He surely has his own life.
Same goes for you living
with your husbands .
You raise children,
run the household,
and do things in the incorporation
with your husband.
but you also come here to listen to
the teachings and practice and so on.
You also need to have your own life, no?
(Audience : Yes)
Yet if your husband says
you ought to stay home
or asks why you go to the temple,
Why volunteer when it doesn't
bring in any income, etc.
If he points out all the things
repeatedly, You won't have your own life.
You can't live your life
according to his wishes.
Eat when he tells you to eat,
stay home when he tells you to do.
Are you able to live
under such conditions?
How do you stress out because of
such things and often ask for advice?
Likewise, husbands have
their own lives too.
You may not like what he does,
but those are your thoughts.
He has his own thoughts, too.
Therefore, even though you live together,
you ought to respect his individuality.
I am not saying just leave him to do
whatever he likes.
But you need to respect certain things
such as his own beliefs or convictions.
But you only see from your perspective.
"When the work is over,
why did you go out for drinks
instead of coming home straightly?"
"Why did you meet your friends?"
"Why you have to go to that funeral?"
"Why did you help
your friend with moving?"
You are not working, so you only need to
take care of home and family,
But when you work, there are
many social relationships.
It's the same with me.
For example, the priests, clergymen
and many others visit here
during Buddha's Birthday event.
You just notice that other
religious leaders come to visit.
And you may think that's all.
But for me, I have to return
the favors, don't I?
So, I get busier during Christmas days
than I am on Buddha's birthday.
(Audience Laughter)
If three clergymen came here,
how many churches do I have to visit
on Christmas?
I have to visit three churches.
If two priests came,
I have to go to two cathedrals.
Since the catholics and the protestants
celebrate the same Christmas,
how many places
do I need to go? Five
Three places on the 25th,
and two places on Christmas eve.
Nothing is free in this world.
You just donate money but in my
case, I can't do that with money.
When a guest pays me a visit for our
special event, I have to attend his event.
Otherwise, the relationship
will discontinue.
That's why I get busy.
But those who don't have such
relationships wonder why I do such things
"Why does a buddhist monk
go to church on Christmas?"
They may think this but that is
not how the world works.
I would have to give up the interfaith
relationships if I didn't do that.
Do you understand what I mean?
And so you should not think
about your perspective only.
Other people have lives and
relationships that do not include you.
Knowing this, if you saw your parents
arguing a lot when you were a child,
and you tell me that you were
wounded by that, what do I say?
I say, "What's that got to do with you?"
They are parents to you but they are
a married couple to each other.
You can see now as an adult that
couples do argue, right? Yes, they do.
"Even though I was hurt
when I was a child,
I can see that
married people can argue."
"That is why my parents argued."
"Since I was so young and immature,
I just thought people shouldn't argue.
Now I know that people do argue"
Thinking this way, your childhood
wound can disappear right away.
This is why I say, "What does the
couple's arguing have to do with you?"
When your son and his wife argue,
you have nothing to do with it, right?
So, just watch them
as a cow watches a chicken.
If it's not easy, what to do?
Quietly, leave the house.
Come back after the argue is over.
If one party says this, just listen
and say yes. Same with the other party.
Don't comment on anything;
just say yes, yes, sure.
Just go along with things this way.
You should not get involved deeply
and take someone's side.
That is how I just listen to your woes.
Even when you cry and
badmouth your husbands.
(Audience Laughter)
You should not get involved
in other people's' lives that much.
It won't be helpful to them
and it will only distress you.